Guide to the Rice University Women's Studies records, 1975-1999 UA 344
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Rice University Center for the Study of Women, Gender, and Sexualtiy records
1975-1999
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Riedel, Brian
UA 344
2 Linear Feet (4 boxes plus digital content)
The collection consists of materials documenting the beginning of Women's Studies as an academic discipline at Rice University. In addition there are materials describing Rice Women's Conferences that took place in 1996 and 1999. The collection also includes a set of audio cassette-recorded interviews with attendees at the 1996 conference.
Biographical / Historical
The history of Women's Studies at Rice can be said to begin in 1983 when Dean of Humanities Allen Matusow returned from a conference in Wisconsin with a sense that Rice was behind the times in relation to this field. Under the leadership of Paula Sanders (history) and Elizabeth Long (sociology), women faculty from various departments—including sociology, history, English, and music—organized a joint study project known as the Faculty Feminist Reading Group, which met several times a semester and brought a few nationally known feminist scholars to campus for public presentations. In 1985 the university hired its first faculty member whose research was dedicated to Women's Studies. This was Jane Gallop, now a Distinguished Professor of English at the University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee.
In 1990 Helen Longino, subsequently chair of Stanford University's Philosophy Department, was hired by Rice and guided establishment in 1992 of the undergraduate major in the Study of Women and Gender, one of Rice's first interdisciplinary majors.
Having become known as the Program for the Study of Women and Gender, the discipline added "sexuality" to its title in 2005. In 2006 the Program was made a Center, and Rosemary Hennessy, the author of three books on materialist feminism and sexual identities in late capitalism, was brought to Rice to head the Center. Establishment of the Center brought together various expressions of feminist studies on campus, including the peer-reviewed journal Feminist Economics, which was founded in 1995 and continues to be overseen by Diana Strassman, its founding editor. She is also director of the Program on Poverty, Justice, and Human Capabilities, included in the curriculum as a minor in 2006.
In addition to the undergraduate major, the Center offers the Graduate Certificate Program, established in 2004. The curriculum represents an educational philosophy centered on "engaged research." Majors can write a thesis or, beginning in 2008, conduct a research project in partnership with a Houston nonprofit organization. Director Hennessy explains, "For us it means a project that is developed in a collaborative and reciprocal relationship with the clients who are served by this nonprofit." In the first four years of this project, more than 40 students had been matched with 27 Houston-area nonprofit organizations. Research projects ranged from evaluating anti-bullying policies in high schools to educating low-pay workers about the labor laws in Texas. In 2012 the Sherry Matusoff Merfish Award was established to recognize students who show exceptional commitment to social justice or engaged research on an issue pertaining to women, gender, or sexuality.
To mark the twentieth anniversary of Women's Studies at Rice, on November 9 and 10, 2012, the Center held a celebration that featured a graduate student panel and a day-long symposium in which current and former directors participated. Present were Jane Gallop, Distinguished Professor of English, University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee; Helen Longino, the Clarence Irving Lewis Professor and Chair of the Department of Philosophy, Stanford University; Paula Sanders, vice provost for academic affairs, dean of graduate and postdoctoral studies, and professor of history, Rice University; Helena Michie, the Agnes Cullen Arnold Professor in Humanities and professor of English, Rice University; Lynne Huffer, the Samuel Candler Dobbs Professor of Women's, Gender, and Sexuality Studies, Emory University; Lora Wildenthal, associate professor of history and chair of the History Department, Rice University; Elora Shehabuddin, associate professor of humanities and political science, Rice University; and Rosemary Hennessy, the L. H. Favrot Professor of Humanities, professor of English and Center for the Study of Women, Gender, and Sexuality director.
The Center has grown to include 47 faculty affiliates from seventeen departments and three divisions: Humanities, Social Sciences, and the Shepherd School of Music. Also included are visiting scholars, postdoctoral fellows, graduate fellows, graduate assistants, and staff. In addition to its many undergraduate and graduate courses, the Center provides two public lecture series: the Gray/Warow Lectures in Health and Well-being, and the Marian Fox Martel Lectures in Gender and Science. Beyond these series, other acclaimed authors and scholars are brought to campus for their contributions to the study of women, gender, and sexuality.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of records having to do with the study of women at Rice. The earliest item is a 1975 speech by sociology Professor Chandler Davidson. The beginnings of Women's Studies as an academic discipline at Rice are recorded in documents dating from 1985 through 1990. Materials from the 1996 Rice Women's Conference are included. One aspect of this event was an oral history project which yielded 28 audio cassette-recorded interviews that are a part of the collection. Materials from a similar conference that took place in 1999 are also included, as is information for planning a subsequent women's conference.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Stored offsite at the Library Service Center and require 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred in 2013 by Dr. Brian Riedel (Professor in the Practice, Asst Director, Center for Women, Gender & Sexuality) and Dr. Linda Driskill (Professor Emeritus, Adjunct Research Professor, English), Rice University.
Index Terms
Subjects
Universities and colleges; Women's studies; Rice University -- History; Women
Document Types
audiotapes; oral histories (document genres)
Subjects (Persons)
Riedel, Brian
- Series I: Records, 1975-1999; 173992
  - 1975 speech by Chandler Davidson: "Women and Other Minorities at Rice", 173994 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Women's Studies 1985-1987, 173995 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Women's Studies speakers 1987-1988, 173996 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Faculty Feminist Reading Group 1988-1989, 173997 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Women's Studies 1988-1989, Coherent Minor Proposal, 173998 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Faculty Feminist Reading Group, planning for 1989-1990, 173999 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1996 Women's Oral History Project documentation, 174000 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1996 Women's Oral History Project, consent forms, 174001 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1996 Rice Women's Conference, publicity, program, participants, 174002 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1999 Rice Women's Conference, 174003 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Planning for future Rice Women's Conference, 174004 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Series II: Interview audio files and transcripts, 1989 and 1996, 173993
  - Boone, Susan (class of 1977, U.T.) wrc04086, 174005 (Box 2, Item 1)
    General
    No consent form exists for this interview. It is not available online, but can accessed through the Woodson Research Center, woodson@rice.edu.
  - Burrus, Sidney (class of 1957) wrc04087, 174006 (Box 2, Item 2)
  - Cole, Allyce Tinsley (class of 1953) interview wrc04088, 174007 (Box 2, Item 3)
  - Coleman, Barbara Forester (class of 1957) wrc04089, 174008 (Box 2, Item 4)
  - Collins, Donna (wrc04197), 176038 (Box 2, Item 5)
  - Cornelius, Jean (class of 1954) interview wrc04090, 174009 (Box 2, Item 6)
  - Cousins, Kelli (class of 1998) wrc04091, 174010 (Box 2, Item 7)
  - Hall, Peggy Margaret (class of 1952) wrc04092, 174011 (Box 2, Item 8)
  - Haraway, Donna (interviewed April 1989) wrc04093, 174012 (Box 2, Item 9)
  - Hatcher, Tilly (class of 1998) wrc04094, 174013 (Box 3, Item 1)
  - Havens, Helen (class of 1955) wrc04095, 174014 (Box 3, Item 2)
  - Lacey, Elsa (Masters in 1971) wrc04096, 174015 (Box 3, Item 3)
  - Ladner, Emily (class of 1937) wrc04097, 174016 (Box 3, Item 4)
  - Lentz, Jacqueline M. (1982-1987) wrc04098, 174017 (Box 3, Item 5)
  - Lloyd, Marianne (class of 1986) interview wrc04099, 174018 (Box 3, Item 6)
  - Mayur, Neela Marathe (class of 1974) interview wrc04100, 174019 (Box 3, Item 7)
  - Misner, Donna (Collins) (class of 1970) interview wrc04197, 174020 (Box 3, Item 8)
  - Morin, Sylvia (class of 1997) interview wrc04198, 174021 (Box 3, Item 9)
  - Much, Kathleen (class of 1963) interview wrc04199, 174022 (Box 3, Item 10)
  - Poindexter, Hally (class of 1947) interview wrc04200, 174023 (Box 3, Item 11)
  - Pounds, Joyce (class of 1945) interview wrc04201, 174024 (Box 4, Item 1)
  - Rindosh, Carolyn (class of 1974) interview wrc04202, 174025 (Box 4, Item 2)
  - Rogers, Karen Hess (class of 1968) interview wrc04203, 174026 (Box 4, Item 3)
  - Smith, Cambria (class of 1996) interview wrc04204, 174027 (Box 4, Item 4)
  - Solomon, Jan (class of 1974) interview wrc04205, 174028 (Box 4, Item 5)
  - Tucker, Jennifer (class of 1994) interview wrc04206, 174029 (Box 4, Item 6)
  - Tucker-Kinney, Mica (class of 1981) interview wrc04207, 174030 (Box 4, Item 7)
  - Volmer, Amy Chang (class of 1977) interview wrc04208, 174031 (Box 4, Item 8)
  - Wilson, Alyson Gabbard (class of 1989) interview wrc04209, 174032 (Box 4, Item 9)
  - Wyman, Cathy Keneda (class of 1974) interview wrc04210, 174033 (Box 4, Item 10)